<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alexander Albury | Alexander W. Albury</title>
    <link>/author/alexander-albury/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/alexander-albury/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Alexander Albury</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/author/alexander-albury/avatar_hu945775e9d1d67b5cfdb45e707a7dee4a_165631_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Alexander Albury</title>
      <link>/author/alexander-albury/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>You’re not tone deaf and you know more about music than you think</title>
      <link>/post/statistical-learning-theconversation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/statistical-learning-theconversation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Think of the last time you were at a birthday party and the obligatory rendition of “Happy Birthday” began. If you’re like most people, you probably joined in without a second thought. Would you be surprised to know that the version of “Happy Birthday” you’re used to singing might be different every time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The musical key that “Happy Birthday” is sung in often depends on the note that the person who starts the song chooses to sing first. This starting point determines the key for the rest of the song. We’re still able to recognize the song because the intervals — the differences in pitch between notes — remain the same and the notes just shift up or down depending on where that starting point is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This act of shifting pitches up or down but preserving the intervals between notes is called transposition and although it may not seem like a simple task, people tend to handle it quite well. In one study, both children and adults easily recognized common songs like “Happy Birthday” and “Twinkle Twinkle Little Star” after they were presented at various keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How is it that most people can perform this complex musical task even in the absence of any formal musical training? Even though you may not realize it, you actually have a lot more musical knowledge than you might think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pattern-recognition&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pattern Recognition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where does this knowledge of music come from? You get it from your everyday life without realizing it thanks to a process called statistical learning. This concept suggests that we learn about our environment through passive exposure and that we constantly use this knowledge to interpret the world around us. Statistical learning is how we learn to recognize patterns and can be used to explain complex learning processes like language acquisition. Significantly, this process is almost entirely subconscious — we learn just by being exposed to new information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of music, we have no shortage of experience to draw from. We hear music constantly, whether intentionally or as a bystander. Riding in a car, standing in an elevator, sitting in a waiting room — we can’t help but be exposed to music. And we gain something from this passive exposure: We become familiar with the patterns and regularities of the music of our culture and we develop an implicit knowledge of music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process happens very early on. Eight-month-old babies can recognize patterns in sequences of tones and some studies show that even at three months of age, babies can recognize changes in short melodies. This implicit musical knowledge only grows as we get older and is why most people might not be as musically challenged as they think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one study, people were recruited to sing in a public park and their performance was compared to that of professional singers. The results showed that the amateur singers’ pitch and timing accuracy was close to that of experts. This aligns with other research showing that people without musical training also perform well on pitch discrimination tasks in which they have to recognize the difference between two tones that vary slightly in pitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These results might seem surprising at first, but they are backed by large-scale studies as well. While many people might claim to be tone deaf, some research estimates that the rate of congenital amusia — a condition in which a person is unable to recognize or process musical information — is less than two per cent in the general population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cultural-expectations&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Expectations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our implicit knowledge of music also leads us to develop expectations of how music should sound. That’s why music from other cultures might sound strange at first — it deviates from the expectations you’ve developed based on the music of your own culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also true across musical genres. Jazz musicians were found to be more accurate at predicting changes in jazz music than classical musicians and non-musicians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our expectations are also responsible for generating musical pleasure and the desire to move when listening to music, and have been used as a tool by artists and composers for centuries to elicit stronger emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So although you might not be aware of it, you’re a walking music processing machine. And next time you find yourself singing “Happy Birthday,” you can sing a bit more confidently with your hidden music expertise in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Article originally published by &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/youre-not-tone-deaf-and-you-know-more-about-music-than-you-think-174453&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Conversation Canada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Data Science Online - A Blessing or a Curse?</title>
      <link>/post/teaching-data-science-gps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/teaching-data-science-gps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Teaching data science online has revealed some useful strategies to be continued as we transition back to in-person teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gauging interest, encouraging engagement, and monitoring understanding all become a challenge when your audience is reduced to a grid of black rectangles. These challenges only increase for subjects where interaction and engagement are key elements in the learning process, including programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming is, at its core, a skill-based subject. While we might be able to listen to and understand a data science tutorial, trying to replicate programming techniques after only watching them would be like trying to play the violin after attending a symphony. Considering the importance of active participation in programming education, a situation in which student engagement is decreased becomes especially detrimental.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few best practices from my experience leading data science workshops, that I believe can make the learning process smoother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;minimize-tech-issues&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimize Tech Issues&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech issues can be discouraging even in the best of times and might lead to disengagement or drop-outs. It’s important to remove as many potential hurdles for students as possible. Although giving learners installation and prep instructions beforehand is good practice, you need to be prepared for the very real possibility that students are coming with zero preparation, particularly for one-time events like workshops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this reason, I try to make sure that every resource I use in my workshops is easily accessible online. Through services such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://mybinder.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;binder&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://research.google.com/colaboratory/faq.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Colab&lt;/a&gt;, even the software used in workshops, including R and Python, can be accessed online, thereby eliminating the risk of installation issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If possible, even the data used in workshops should be accessible online without the need to download it. This avoids problems related to folders, file paths, and working directories; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theverge.com/22684730/students-file-folder-directory-structure-education-gen-z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;concepts that might be less intuitive than you think&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By removing these initial barriers, you can spend more time on content instead of debugging installation and download issues which are often hyper-specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;engage-participants&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage Participants&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to improve interaction online is to make learners more invested in the content. Giving students control over their learning experience is a great way to promote autonomy and make them more active participants. One of the techniques I like to employ in data science is to give students choices over which data we use in a lesson. This interactivity helps to tailor content to student interests and leads to increased engagement and participation, when combined with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.concordia.ca/ctl/digital-teaching/usign-zoom-engage-students.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zoom tools such as polls and reactions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;see-things-from-a-learners-perspective&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;See Things from a Learner&amp;rsquo;s Perspective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that learners don’t share your technology setup. So although you might have created the perfect work-from-home command centre, you should consider that many of your students will be viewing your content on a 13-inch laptop screen. This is an important consideration when deciding how to organize windows, which font size to use, and how to format slides. You might even want to go as far as joining your workshop on another computer so you can see what students see. Not only does this aid learning by making your material easier to follow, but it can also address important &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.concordia.ca/students/accessibility/faculty-information/universal-design-for-learning.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;accessibility needs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online learning also gives us the opportunity to literally share the learner’s perspective. Anyone who has led a small, in-person workshop in tech or data science has likely had the experience of bouncing back and forth across the room, inspecting code and troubleshooting errors. Conversely, anyone who has tried troubleshooting remotely knows how frustrating it can be. One of the few benefits of online learning is the increased prevalence of screen-sharing. Screen-sharing allows not just the instructor but all of the other participants to be a part of the debugging process (provided that they are comfortable sharing their screen). This collaborative debugging can be a learning activity in itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;looking-towards-the-future&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Towards the Future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, what stands out is that most of these techniques don’t need to be reserved for online learning. Although remote teaching might have pushed us to optimize our teaching techniques, there’s no reason we can’t take what we’ve learned back to in-person classes. And as we make this transition, we’ll have the opportunity to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.concordia.ca/ctl/teaching/blended-learning.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blended learning approaches&lt;/a&gt;, allowing us to draw from the best of both worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Article originally published on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.concordia.ca/cunews/offices/vprgs/gradproskills/blogs/2022/01/27/teaching-data-science-online-a-blessing-or-a-curse.html?c=students/gradproskills/blog&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GradProSkills Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example preprint / working paper</title>
      <link>/publication/preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/preprint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example journal article</title>
      <link>/publication/journal-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/journal-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example conference paper</title>
      <link>/publication/conference-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/conference-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code, math, and images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
